A Guide to the Eloise Word Skewis Collection 1777-1907
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Eloise Word Skewis Collection 1777-1907
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 30
1 Hollinger Document Case, 1 Oversize Box, 1 tubular poster container. 2.1 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eloise Word Skewis, April 1979.
Biographical/Historical Information
The dominant family branch for Eloise Word Skewis are the Claiborne family of New England and America. Other branches include the Kilby and the Harrison families of the James River.
The Claiborne family of England and America are an ancient family that derived its name from the manor of Cleburne or Cliborne in Westmoreland, England, near the river of Eden. The manor is named in Doomsday Book (A.D.1086) and the family were for many generations lords of this place. The first of the line appearing in pedigrees is Hervey, to whom Henry II granted moiety of the manor of Cliborne.
The first of the Claiborne line to come to America was William Claiborne. He was born about 1587 and is first noticed in June 1621, when the Virginia Company engaged him to go to Virginia as surveyor. William came to Virginia with Governor Wyatt in 1621. In 1625 Governor Yeardley appointed him Secretary of State for the Colony and member of the Council. In 1642, the King appointed William as Treasurer of Virginia for life. He held several other public offices throughout his life. In 1631, William created a trading settlement on Kent Island in the Chesapeake. There he held many business contacts with several persons in London.
Scope and Content Information
The material in this collection dates from 1777 to 1907. This material includes personal and business correspondence, legal documents, newspaper clippings, and other personal and business papers. Of particular historical note are originals of Confederate currency and bonds. Of genealogical significance are family trees for the Claiborne and the Harrison families.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically within each series and subseries.
Organization
This collection is divided into four series: I. Correspondence; II. Legal and Business Papers; III. Newspaper Clippings; and IV. Miscellaneous.
Series I: Correspondence is divided into two subseries: A. Personal and B. Business.
Subseries A: Personal. Contains personal correspondence dating from 1853 to 1907. The material is mainly correspondence among family members.
Subseries B: Business contains business correspondence dating from 1842 to 1907. This material is primarily related to purchases, money owed, and workers.
Series II: Legal and Business Papers is divided into two subseries: A. Legal Papers and B. Business Papers.
Subseries A: Legal Papers. Contains deeds, contracts, receipts, and court documents dating from 1777 to 1886,
Subseries B: Business Papers. Contains tax documents, receipts, bank statements, bonds, promissory notes, credit bills, stock and bond certificates, certificates of indebtedness, bank notes, account books, and court orders dating from 1800 to 1899.
Series III: Newspaper Clippings contains a small number of undated and miscellaneous newspaper clippings, probably from the Baltimore Sun.
Series IV: Miscellaneous contains various miscellaneous and oversize items. Included are original Confederate currency and bonds, membership certificates for the Daughters of the American Revolution, an 1868 Life Insurance policy, an 1787 land indenture, and family trees for the Claiborne family of England and America and the Harrison family of James River.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Martha Finley to Mrs. Lucy Terry, January 8, 1853 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John F. Claiborne to Cousin Bill, September 19, 1853 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B.B. Walker to Colonel William C. Grasty, July 12, 1855 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - John L. Grasty to "My dear Brother", September 18, 1855 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Thomas Kilby to James Kilby, July 24, 1879 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lou (?) to "My dear Father," December 7, 1879 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From Daniel Scott to Mr. Reed, August 19, 1907 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Original Valentine greeting to James Kilby, February 14 (year unknown) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence
    - William L. Pannill to Mr. Joesph Dickinson, October 19, 1842 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - E.D. Wallis to Colonel William Rison, May 18, 1857 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Kent Paine to Messrs. Grasty and Rison, November 13, 1860 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Samuel O. Hicks to Messrs. Grasty and Rison, December 15, 1860 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Murray, Finney, and Shelton to Grasty and Rison, February 12, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A.B. Rucker to Messrs. Grasty and Rison, February 16, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A.Y. Stokes to Messrs. Grasty and Rison, May 1, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From John S. Reese to Messrs. Grasty and Rison, January 31, 1866 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - B.P. Baker to James R. Saunders (a survey of a piece of land), December 12, 1871 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From George Reed to James T. Kilby, August 28, 1907 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
- Legal and Business Papers
  - Legal Papers
    - Copy of a legal document, Lunenburg County, Virginia in regard to the estate of the late Lightfoot Calliham, April 14, 1777 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Inventory and appraisment of the estate of Lightfoot Calliham, Lunenburg County, Virginia recorded in the court held for Lunenburg County, December 10, 1778 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Promissory Note of John Faris to Narfieto Scruggs one pound, five shillings, six pence, March 18, 1808 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Note of James Mustain of Pittsylvania County to Phillip L. Grasty of the same county (promissory note), May 22, 1811 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Indenture (deed) between William Russell of Pittsylvania County and John Holliway wherby Holliway held certain property in trust as a security for the payment of a debt to Daniel and Obediah P. Terry also of Pittsylvania County, March 19, 1813 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Note signed by Jeremiah Compton for sum of money owed to Phillip L. Grasty of Pittsylvania County, Virginia, August 26, 1818 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Deed of Bargain and Sale from George and Maria Tucker to George Johnson (property in Danville Virginia), December 19, 1818 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Copy of a judgment in the case of Knox v. Martin, 1818 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract between William C. Franklin of Pittsylvania County and Samuel Stone of Danville for the hire of a Negro (slave) for the year 1827, December 29, 1826 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Contract for the hire of a negro slave girl for the year 1830 between Moses Echols and Issac Allen, 1830 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deed of gift from James Garland of Pittsylvania County, Virginia to his niece Jane Augustus James Garland Stone conveying to her Moriah (a slave) and her two infant children (about three weeks old), April 26, 1831 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Record of a friendly suit in chancery brought by Preston Hardy and Lewis Hardy of Jackson County, Georgia against John Hardy of Pittsylvania County VA, excutor of the estate of Benjamin Hardy, October 15, 1836 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bill of Complaint of Eustace Hunt in the county court of Pittsylvania County, Virginia (a copy), 1841 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A list of property given Mrs. Eliza Catharine Robinson, Samuel H. Williams, Trustee, September 23, 1842 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deed between James R. Saunders and his wife Diana and Virginius S. Kilby and his wife Ophelia conveying c. 200 acres of land in Cypress Township Nansemond County to the Kilbys, July 10, 1871 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Copy of a court order, Pittslyvania Circuit Court; Bank of Virginia and plantiffs vs. Edward I. Collier and Defendants, September 16, 1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deed of Bargain and Sale-Jerusha Norfleet to Thomas Kilby-property in Suffolk, Virginia, March 6, 1875 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deed between David S. Keen and Phillip L. Grasty, all of Pittsylvania County, VA. transferring a tract of 99-1/2 acres of land in Pittsylvania (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Memorandum of articles left by Mr. Collins to divide between A.M. Kilby, Patsey Kilby and Lizzy Smith (n.d.) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Will of Harriet Collins-distribution of personal articles, undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business Papers
    - List of taxes owed by Mr. James Garland in the county court of Franklin, September 1, 1812 to September 1, 1813 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Receipt for payment-Jonathan Jones to the clerk of Henry County Court, 1815 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Statement of account of W. Barnett with Samuel Stone, August-December 1815 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Statement of account of Mr. Robert C. Carter with Samuel Stone, June-November 1819 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Statement of account of Mr. W.L. Quinn with Samuel Stone, November 1819 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Note listing a certificate, counterfeit note, etc... (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Receipt for payment of a judgment obtained against John Henry, January 17, 1820 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of account of Messrs. Lewis and Cabell with Samuel Stone, February 28, 1820 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of account of Mr. James Garland with James H. Williams, January, 1822-January 1, 1823 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of account of Mr. James Garland with James H. Williams, 1822-1823 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Receipt of G.H. Thompson for payment from James Garland, March 18, 1823 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Copy of a court order of Pittsylvania County Superior Court, that James F. Quinn pay Samuel Stone his expenses as a witness, September 1825 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Copy of a court order of Pittsylvania County Superior Court, that James F. Quinn pay Samuel Stone's expenses as a witness, September 1825 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statment of legal expenses-Phillip L. Grasty, January 1826 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of account of Captain James M. Williams with Samuel Stone, 1828-1834 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Statement of account of Mr. James Garland with James H. Stone, 1829 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Promissory Note-J. Garland to Samuel Stone, August 6, 1831 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Receipt on the inspectors at Pannills Warehouse for charges incurred in the storage of tobacco by Stone and Pannill, October, 1831 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Receipt on the inspectors at Pannills Warehouse for charges incurred in the storage of tobacco by Stone and Pannill, October, 1831 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Statement of account Claiborne with Wilson (?), 1832-1834 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Statement of account Sam Stone with Sam Panhill, 1834 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Statement of account Captain William Worsham with S. Ellis, 1834-1837 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Statement of account Samuel Stone by Hagood, Neal, and Williams, April-November, 1836 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Receipt for payment by Messrs. Hagood and Claiborne to Len Ganett and Sons, March 15, 1837 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - List of H.I. Claiborne's credit bills, Spring, 1837 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account of James Garlant (Garland?) with Thomas Davis, June-December, 1837 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account of Captain Samuel Stone with Hagood and Claiborne, April 1837-January 1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Reciept for $1,050.00 paid by Samuel Claiborne to Samuel Stone for the purpose of buying slaves, March 1838 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account of Stephen R. Neal with Captain Samuel Stone, 1838-1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account of Messrs. Goderick and Tally with William Rison, December 1838-February 1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account Hagood and Claiborne with Captain Samuel Stone, 1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Statement of account for the Purchase of a Negro, June 2, 1839 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cashier of the Danville office of the Bank of Virginia-note to William Worsham, March 30, 1840 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Receipt for payment by postmaster William Grasty at Mount Airy, Virginia, July 10, 1840 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bill for the sale of a barouch (sic) plus interest nine years overdue from E. Rosson to Mr. Whitmell P. Tunstali, March 23, 1841 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Statement of Account for the year services provided by Elijah Rosson for James and Allen Jones, 1843 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Receipt for payment of $400.00 by Samuel Stone as part of a judgment against him brought by Stone Enos, 1843 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Statment of account of Messrs. S. and William Ayres with Samuel Stone, August-October, 1843 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Statement of account of Robert Williams with Captain Samuel Stone, 1843-1844 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Report by James L. Denny, cashier of the Bank of Virginia office at Danville, of a list of bonds deposited by John Dickinson, trustee for William Linn-when collected, the bonds were to be applied to Mr. William Linn's debt, January 13, 1844 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Receipt for $5.49 received from B.B. Walker, Postmaster at Mount Airy Virginia, by Robert M. Jordan-Note written by Robert Jordan on reverse side, July 2, 1849 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stock certificate of Suffolk Savings Bank-Thomas J. Kilby, September 1, 1852 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Reciept for $250.00 paid by Thomas J. Kilby on a bond held by David B. Beaton against Benjamin Riddick, April 23, 1853 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Receipt for payment by Thomas J. Kilby on a bond held by David Beaton against Benjamin Riddick, June 30, 1855 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Receipt for payment by Thomas J. Kilby, on a bond held by David E. Beaton against Benjamin Riddick, February 1856 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Receipt for payment by William Rison to George W. Trent, August 26, 1856 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Message of the agent of Richmond and Danville Railroad, addressed to Grasty and Rison, December 18, 1857 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Receipt for payment by William C. Grasty to John S. Glasgow, August, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $200.00 in Confederate bonds, by Samuel Ward, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $200.00 in Confederate bonds, by John Batten, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $1,000.00 in Confederate bonds, by Albert Brinkley, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $2,300.00 in Confederate bonds, by Mills Rodgers, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $300.00 in Confederate bonds, by Jonas Wilkins, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $1,000.00 in Confederate bonds, by John F. Pinner, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $600.00 in Confederate bonds, by James Riddick of Williamsburg (?), Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Certificate for purchase of $100.00 in Confederate bonds, by Amos Harrell, Petersburg, Virginia, March 19, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stock certificate indicating that T.J. Kilby has fity-two shares of stock in the Bank of the City of Petersburg, March 22, 1864 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Receipt for payment in full of a life insurance policy for Thomas J. Kilby, April 13, 1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Certificate of indebtedness of the Commonwealth of Virginia to Thomas Kilby-unpaid interest on the regular debt, July 1, 1872-September 5, 1873 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - A stock certificate for one share in The Suffolk Collegiate Institute. The stock was owned by Kilby, Parker, and Co. of Suffolk, September 29, 1876 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Note of V. S. Kilby for $1,000 owed to Thomas J. Kilby, May 29, 1877 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Savings Account book-The Farmers Bank of Nansemond, Suffolk, Virginia-account of V.S. Kilby, 1889 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Stock Certificate-The Suffolk Street Railway Company of Suffolk, Virginia-one share-Virginius S. Kilby, June 13, 1893 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Assorted Clippings-probably from the Baltimore Sun (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clipping in re: estate of William Keyser (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clipping in re: Union Army and Confederate Army strength (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous
  - Confederate Currency-$5.00 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - $200.00 bond of the Confederate States of America (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notification of membership in the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution for Miss Jennie Clark Grasty, November 7, 1899 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Envelope of sketches and paper cut outs (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Confederate bond for $500.00 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Facsimile copy of the bail bond of Jefferson Davis, accepted by U.S. Court at Richmond, November, 1867 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Envelope containing art work (Oversize Box 2)
  - Pittsylvania County of Virginia Post Office Account Statement, December 31, 1843-March 31, 1844 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution membership certificate for Mrs. Mary Claiborne Kilby, 1906 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Piedmont Real Estate Insurance Company Life, Insurance Policy for Thomas Jefferson Kilby, 1868 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Indenture for the lands of John Owen, Deceased, 1787 (Oversize Box 2)
  - Family Tree for the Harrisons of the James River (Oversize Container 1)
  - Family Tree for the Claibornes of England and America (Oversize Container 1)